<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="amqp">
  <title>Using Spring AMQP</title>

  <para>In this chapter, we will explore interface and classes that are the
  essential components for developing applications with Spring AMQP.</para>

  <sect1>
    <title>AMQP Abstractions</title>

    <para>The Spring AMQP project consists of a handful of modules, each
    represented by a JAR in the distribution. These modules are: spring-amqp,
    spring-rabbit, spring-erlang, and spring-rabbit-admin. The 'spring-amqp'
    module contains the org.springframework.amqp.core package. Within that
    package, you will find the classes that represent the core AMQP "model".
    Our intention is to provide generic abstractions that do not rely on any
    particular AMQP broker implementation or client library. End user code
    will be more portable across vendor implementations as it can be developed
    against the abstraction layer only. These abstractions are then used
    implemented by broker-specific modules, such as 'spring-rabbit'. For the
    M1 release there is only a RabbitMQ implementation however the
    abstractions have been vetted in .NET using Apache Qpid in addition to
    RabbitMQ.</para>

    <para>The overview here assumes that you are already familiar with the
    basics of the AMQP specification already. If you are not, then have a look
    at the resources listed in <xref linkend="resources" /></para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Message</title>

      <para>The 0-8 and 0-9-1 AMQP specifications do not define an Message
      class or interface. Instead, when performing an operation such as
      '<literal>
          <methodname>basicPublish</methodname>
        </literal>', the content is passed as a byte-array argument and
      additional properties are passed in as separate arguments. Spring AMQP
      defines a Message class as part of a more general AMQP domain model
      representation. The purpose of the Message class is to simply
      encapsulate the body and properties within a single instance so that the
      API can in turn be simpler. The Message class definition is quite
      straightforward.</para>

      <programlisting language="java">public class Message {

    private final MessageProperties messageProperties;

    private final byte[] body;

    public Message(byte[] body, MessageProperties messageProperties) {
        this.body = body;
        this.messageProperties = messageProperties;
    }

    public byte[] getBody() {
        return this.body;
    }

    public MessageProperties getMessageProperties() {
        return this.messageProperties;
}</programlisting>

      <para>The <interfacename>MessageProperties</interfacename> interface
      defines several common properties such as 'messageId', 'timestamp',
      'contentType', and several more. Those properties can also be extended
      with user-defined 'headers' by calling the <methodname>setHeader(String
      key, Object value)</methodname> method.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Exchange</title>

      <para>The <interfacename>Exchange</interfacename> interface represents
      an AMQP Exchange, which is what a Message Producer sends to. Each
      Exchange within a virtual host of a broker will have a unique name as
      well as a few other properties:</para>

      <programlisting language="java">public interface Exchange {

    String getName();

    ExchangeType getExchangeType();

    boolean isDurable();

    boolean isAutoDelete();

    Map&lt;String, Object&gt; getArguments();

}</programlisting>

      <para>As you can see, an Exchange also has a 'type' represented by the
      enumeration <classname>ExchangeType</classname>. The basic types are:
      <literal>Direct</literal>, <literal>Topic</literal> and
      <literal>Fanout</literal>. In the core package you will find
      implementations of the <interfacename>Exchange</interfacename> interface
      for each of those types. The behavior varies across these Exchange types
      in terms of how they handle bindings to Queues. A Direct exchange allows
      for a Queue to be bound by a fixed routing key (often the Queue's name).
      A Topic exchange supports bindings with routing patterns that may
      include the '*' and '#' wildcards for 'exactly-one' and 'zero-or-more',
      respectively. The Fanout exchange publishes to all Queues that are bound
      to it without taking any routing key into consideration. For much more
      information about Exchange types, check out <xref
      linkend="resources" />.</para>

      <note>
        <para>The AMQP specification also requires that any broker provide a
        "default" Direct Exchange that has no name. All Queues that are
        declared will be bound to that default Exchange with their names as
        routing keys. You will learn more about the default Exchange's usage
        within Spring AMQP in <xref linkend="amqp-template" />.</para>
      </note>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Queue</title>

      <para>The <classname>Queue</classname> class represents the component
      from which a Message Consumer receives Messages. Like the various
      Exchange classes, our implementation is intended to be an abstract
      representation of this core AMQP type.</para>

      <programlisting language="java">public class Queue  {

    private final String name;

    private volatile boolean durable;

    private volatile boolean exclusive;

    private volatile boolean autoDelete;

    private volatile Map&lt;String, Object&gt; arguments;

    public Queue(String name) {
        this.name = name;
    }

    // Getters and Setters omitted for brevity

</programlisting>

      <para>Notice that the constructor takes the Queue name. Depending on the
      implementation, the admin template may provide methods for generating a
      uniquely named Queue. Such Queues can be useful as a "reply-to" address
      or other <emphasis>temporary</emphasis> situations. For that reason, the
      'exclusive' and 'autoDelete' properties of an auto-generated Queue would
      both be set to 'true'.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Binding</title>

      <para>Given that a producer sends to an Exchange and a consumer receives
      from a Queue, the bindings that connect Queues to Exchanges are critical
      for connecting those producers and consumers via messaging. In Spring
      AMQP, we define a <classname>Binding</classname> class to represent
      those connections. Let's review the basic options for binding Queues to
      Exchanges.</para>

      <para>You can bind a Queue to a DirectExchange with a fixed routing
      key.</para>

      <programlisting language="java">new Binding(someQueue, someDirectExchange, "foo.bar")</programlisting>

      <para>You can bind a Queue to a TopicExchange with a routing
      pattern.</para>

      <programlisting language="java">new Binding(someQueue, someTopicExchange, "foo.*")</programlisting>

      <para>You can bind a Queue to a FanoutExchange with no routing
      key.</para>

      <programlisting language="java">new Binding(someQueue, someFanoutExchange)</programlisting>

      <para>We also provide a <classname>BindingBuilder</classname> to
      facilitate a "fluent API" style.</para>

      <programlisting language="java">Binding b = BindingBuilder.from(someQueue).to(someTopicExchange).with("foo.*");</programlisting>

      <note>
        <para>The BindingBuilder class is shown above for clarity, but this
        style works well when using a static import for the 'from()'
        method.</para>
      </note>

      <para>By itself, an instance of the Binding class is just holding the
      data about a connection. In other words, it is not an "active"
      component. However, as you will see later in <xref
      linkend="broker-configuration" />, Binding instances can be used by the
      <interfacename>AmqpAdmin</interfacename> class to actually trigger the
      binding actions on the broker. Also, as you will see in that same
      section, the Binding instances can be defined using Spring's
      <literal>@Bean</literal>-style within <literal>@Configuration</literal>
      classes. There is also a convenient base class which further simplifies
      that approach for generating AMQP-related bean definitions and
      recognizes the Queues, Exchanges, and Bindings so that they will all be
      declared on the AMQP broker upon application startup.</para>
    </sect2>

    <para>The <interfacename>AmqpTemplate</interfacename> is also defined
    within the core package. As one of the main components involved in actual
    AMQP messaging, it is discussed in detail in its own section (see <xref
    linkend="amqp-template" />).</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Connection and Resource Management</title>

    <para>Whereas the AMQP model we described in the previous section is
    generic and applicable to all implementations, when we get into the
    management of resources, the details are specific to the broker
    implementation. Therefore, in this section, we will be focusing on code
    that exists only within our "spring-rabbit" module since at this point,
    RabbitMQ is the only supported implementation.</para>

    <para>The central component for managing a connection to the RabbitMQ
    broker is the <interfacename>ConnectionFactory</interfacename> interface.
    The responsibility of a <interfacename>ConnectionFactory</interfacename>
    implementation is to provide an instance of
    <classname>com.rabbitmq.client.Connection</classname>. The simplest
    implementation we provide is
    <classname>SingleConnectionFactory</classname> which establishes a single
    connection that can be shared by the application. Sharing of the
    connection is possible since the "unit of work" for messaging with AMQP is
    actually a "channel" (in some ways, this is similar to the relationship
    between a Connection and a Session in JMS). As you can imagine, the
    connection instance provides a <methodname>createChannel</methodname>
    method. When creating an instance of
    <classname>SingleConnectionFactory</classname>, the 'hostname' can be
    provided via the constructor. The 'username' and 'password' properties
    should be provided as well.</para>

    <programlisting language="java">SingleConnectionFactory connectionFactory = new SingleConnectionFactory("somehost");
connectionFactory.setUsername("guest");
connectionFactory.setPassword("guest");

Connection connection = connectionFactory.createConnection();</programlisting>

    <para>When using XML, the configuration might look like this:</para>

    <programlisting language="xml">&lt;bean id="cf" class="org.springframework.amqp.rabbit.connection.SingleConnectionFactory"&gt;
    &lt;constructor-arg value="somehost"/&gt;
    &lt;property name="username" value="guest"/&gt;
    &lt;property name="password" value="guest"/&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>

    <para><note>
         You may also discover the 

        <classname>CachingConnectionFactory</classname>

         implementation, but at this time, that code is considered 

        <emphasis>experimental</emphasis>

         . We recommend sticking with 

        <classname>SingleConnectionFactory</classname>

         for now as the caching implementation will most likely evolve. Support for failover of connections is also planned. 
      </note></para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="amqp-template">
    <title>AmqpTemplate</title>

    <para>As with many other high-level abstractions provided by the Spring
    Framework and related projects, Spring AMQP provides a "template" that
    plays a central role. The interface that defines the main operations is
    called <interfacename>AmqpTemplate</interfacename>. Those operations cover
    the general behavior for sending and receiving Messages. In other words,
    they are not unique to any implementation, hence the "AMQP" in the name.
    On the other hand, there are implementations of that interface that are
    tied to implementations of the AMQP protocol. Unlike JMS, which is an
    interface-level API itself, AMQP is a wire-level protocol. The
    implementations of that protocol provide their own client libraries, so
    each implementation of the template interface will depend on a particular
    client library. Currently, there is only a single implementation:
    <classname>RabbitTemplate</classname>. In the examples that follow, you
    will often see usage of an "AmqpTemplate", but when you look at the
    configuration examples, or any code excerpts where the template is
    instantiated and/or setters are invoked, you will see the implementation
    type (e.g. "RabbitTemplate").</para>

    <para>As mentioned above, the <interfacename>AmqpTemplate</interfacename>
    interface defines all of the basic operations for sending and receiving
    Messages. We will explore Message sending and reception, respectively, in
    the two sections that follow.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Sending messages</title>

    <para>When sending a Message, one can use any of the following
    methods:</para>

    <programlisting language="xml">void send(MessageCreator messageCreator) throws AmqpException;

void send(String routingKey, MessageCreator messageCreator) throws AmqpException;

void send(String exchange, String routingKey, MessageCreator messageCreator) throws AmqpException;</programlisting>

    <para>We can begin our discussion with the last method listed above since
    it is actually the most explicit. It allows an AMQP Exchange name to be
    provided at runtime along with a routing key. The last parameter is the
    callback that is responsible for actual creating of the Message instance.
    An example of using this method to send a Message might look this
    this:</para>

    <programlisting language="java">amqpTemplate.send("marketData.topic", "quotes.nasdaq.FOO", new MessageCreator() {
    public Message createMessage() {
        return new Message("12.34".getBytes(), someProperties);
    }
});</programlisting>

    <para>The "exchange" property can be set on the template itself if you
    plan to use that template instance to send to the same exchange most or
    all of the time. In such cases, the second method listed above may be used
    instead. The following example is functionally equivalent to the previous
    one:</para>

    <programlisting language="java">amqpTemplate.setExchange("marketData.topic");
amqpTemplate.send("quotes.nasdaq.FOO", new MessageCreator() {
    public Message createMessage() {
        return new Message("12.34".getBytes(), someProperties);
    }
});</programlisting>

    <para>If both the "exchange" and "routingKey" properties are set on the
    template, then the method accepting only the
    <interfacename>MessageCreator</interfacename> may be used:</para>

    <programlisting language="java">amqpTemplate.setExchange("marketData.topic");
amqpTemplate.setRoutingKey("quotes.nasdaq.FOO");
amqpTemplate.send(new MessageCreator() {
    public Message createMessage() {
        return new Message("12.34".getBytes(), someProperties);
    }
});</programlisting>

    <para>A better way of thinking about the exchange and routing key
    properties is that the explicit method parameters will always override the
    template's default values. In fact, even if you do not explicitly set
    those properties on the template, there are always default values in
    place. In both cases, the default is an empty String, but that is actually
    a sensible default. As far as the routing key is concerned, it's not
    always necessary in the first place (e.g. a Fanout Exchange). Furthermore,
    a Queue may be bound to an Exchange with an empty String. Those are both
    legitimate scenarios for reliance on the default empty String value for
    the routing key property of the template. As far as the Exchange name is
    concerned, the empty String is quite commonly used because the AMQP
    specification defines the "default Exchange" as having no name. Since all
    Queues are automatically bound to that default Exchange (which is a Direct
    Exchange) using their name as the binding value, that second method above
    can be used for simple point-to-point Messaging to any Queue through the
    default Exchange. Simply provide the queue name as the "routingKey" -
    either by providing the method parameter at runtime:</para>

    <programlisting language="java">RabbitTemplate template = new RabbitTemplate(); // using default no-name Exchange
template.send("queue.helloWorld", new MessageCreator() {
    public Message createMessage() {
        return new Message("Hello World".getBytes(), someProperties);
    }
});</programlisting>

    <para>Or, if you prefer to create a template that will be used for
    publishing primarily or exclusively to a single Queue, the following is
    perfectly reasonable:</para>

    <programlisting language="java">RabbitTemplate template = new RabbitTemplate(); // using default no-name Exchange
template.setRoutingKey("queue.helloWorld"); // but we'll always send to this Queue
template.send(new MessageCreator() {
    public Message createMessage() {
        return new Message("Hello World".getBytes(), someProperties);
    }
});</programlisting>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Receiving messages</title>

    <para>Message reception is always a bit more complicated than sending. The
    reason is that there are two ways to receive a Message. The simpler option
    is to poll for a single Message at a time with a synchronous, blocking
    method call. The more complicated yet more common approach is to register
    a listener that will receive Messages on-demand, asynchronously. We will
    look at an example of each approach in the next two sub-sections.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Synchronous Reception</title>

      <para>The <interfacename>AmqpTemplate</interfacename> itself can be used
      for synchronous Message reception. There are two 'receive' methods
      available. As with the Exchange on the sending side, there is a method
      that requires a queue property having been set directly on the template
      itself, and there is a method that accepts a queue parameter at
      runtime.</para>

      <programlisting language="java">Message receive() throws AmqpException;

Message receive(String queueName) throws AmqpException;</programlisting>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
       

      <title>Asynchronous Reception</title>

       

      <para>For asynchronous Message reception, a dedicated component other
      than the <interfacename>AmqpTemplate</interfacename> is involved. That
      component is a container for a Message consuming callback. We will look
      at the container and its properties in just a moment, but first we
      should look at the callback since that is where your application code
      will be integrated with the messaging system. There are a few options
      for the callback. The simplest of these is to implement the
      <interfacename>MessageListener</interfacename> interface:</para>

       

      <programlisting language="java">public interface MessageListener {

    void onMessage(Message message);

}</programlisting>

       

      <para>If your callback logic depends upon the AMQP Channel instance for
      any reason, you may instead use the
      <interfacename>ChannelAwareMessageListener</interfacename>. It looks
      similar but with an extra parameter:</para>

       

      <programlisting language="java">public interface ChannelAwareMessageListener&lt;M extends Message&gt; {

    void onMessage(M message, Channel channel) throws Exception;

}</programlisting>

       

      <para>If you prefer to maintain a stricter separation between your
      application logic and the messaging API, you can rely upon an adapter
      implementation that is provided by the framework. This is often referred
      to as "Message-driven POJO" support. When using the adapter, you only
      need to provide a reference to the instance that the adapter itself
      should invoke.</para>

       

      <programlisting language="java">MessageListener listener = new MessageListenerAdapter(somePojo);</programlisting>

       Now that you've seen the various options for the Message-listening callback, we can turn our attention to the container. Basically, the container handles the "active" responsibilities so that the listener callback can remain passive. The container is an example of a "lifecycle" component. It provides methods for starting and stopping. When configuring the container, you are essentially bridging the gap between an AMQP Queue and the 

      <interfacename>MessageListener</interfacename>

       instance. You must provide a reference to the 

      <interfacename>ConnectionFactory</interfacename>

       and the queue name or Queue instance(s) from which that listener should consume Messages. Here is the most basic example using the default implementation, 

      <classname>SimpleMessageListenerContainer</classname>

       : 

      <programlisting language="java">SimpleMessageListenerContainer container = new SimpleMessageListenerContainer();
container.setConnectionFactory(rabbitConnectionFactory);
container.setQueueName("some.queue");
container.setMessageListener(someListener);</programlisting>

       As an "active" component, it's most common to create the listener container with a bean definition so that it can simply run in the background. This can be done via XML: 

      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;bean class="org.springframework.amqp.rabbit.listener.SimpleMessageListenerContainer"&gt;
    &lt;property name="connectionFactory" ref="rabbitConnectionFactory"/&gt;
    &lt;property name="queueName" value="some.queue"/&gt;
    &lt;property name="messageListener" ref="someListener"/&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>

       Or, you may prefer to use the @Configuration style which will look very similar to the actual code snippet above: 

      <programlisting language="java">@Configuration
public class ExampleAmqpConfiguration {

    @Bean
    public MessageListenerContainer messageListenerContainer { 
        SimpleMessageListenerContainer container = new SimpleMessageListenerContainer();
        container.setConnectionFactory(rabbitConnectionFactory());
        container.setQueueName("some.queue");
        container.setMessageListener(exampleListener());
        return container;
    }

    @Bean
    public ConnectionFactory rabbitConnectionFactory() {
        SingleConnectionFactory connectionFactory = new SingleConnectionFactory("localhost");
        connectionFactory.setUsername("guest");
        connectionFactory.setPassword("guest");
        return connectionFactory;
    }

    @Bean
    public MessageListener exampleListener() {
        return new MessageListener() {
            public void onMessage(Message message) {
                System.out.println("received: " + message)
            }
        }
    }
}</programlisting>

       
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Message Converters</title>

    <para>The <interfacename>AmqpTemplate</interfacename> also defines several
    methods for sending and receiving Messages that will delegate to a
    <interfacename>MessageConverter</interfacename>. The
    <interfacename>MessageConverter</interfacename> itself is quite
    straightforward. It provides a single method for each direction: one for
    converting <emphasis>to</emphasis> a Message and another for converting
    <emphasis>from</emphasis> a Message. Notice that when converting to a
    Message, you may also provide properties in addition to the object. The
    "object" parameter typically corresponds to the Message body.</para>

    <programlisting language="java">public interface MessageConverter {

    Message toMessage(Object object, MessageProperties messageProperties)
            throws MessageConversionException;

    Object fromMessage(Message message) throws MessageConversionException;

}</programlisting>

    <para>The relevant Message-sending methods on the
    <interfacename>AmqpTemplate</interfacename> are listed below. They are
    simpler than the methods we discussed previously because they do not
    require the MessageCreator callback. Instead, the MessageConverter is
    responsible for "creating" each Message by converting the provided object
    to the byte array for the Message body and then adding any provided
    MessageProperties.</para>

    <programlisting language="java">void convertAndSend(Object message) throws AmqpException;

void convertAndSend(String routingKey, Object message) throws AmqpException;

void convertAndSend(String exchange, String routingKey, Object message) throws AmqpException;

void convertAndSend(Object message, MessagePostProcessor messagePostProcessor) throws AmqpException;

void convertAndSend(String routingKey, Object message, MessagePostProcessor messagePostProcessor)
        throws AmqpException;

void convertAndSend(String exchange, String routingKey, Object message,
        MessagePostProcessor messagePostProcessor) throws AmqpException;</programlisting>

    <para>On the receiving side, there are only two methods: one that accepts
    the queue name and one that relies on the template's "queue" property
    having been set.</para>

    <programlisting language="java">Object receiveAndConvert() throws AmqpException;

Object receiveAndConvert(String queueName) throws AmqpException;</programlisting>

    <sect2>
      <title>SimpleMessageConverter</title>

      <para>The default implementation of the
      <interfacename>MessageConverter</interfacename> strategy is called
      <classname>SimpleMessageConverter</classname>. This is the converter
      that will be used by an instance of RabbitTemplate if you do not
      explicitly configure an alternative. It handles text-based content,
      serialized Java objects, and simple byte arrays.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title>Converting From a Message</title>

        <para>If the content type of the input Message begins with "text"
        (e.g. "text/plain"), it will also check for the content-encoding
        property to determine the charset to be used when converting the
        Message body byte array to a Java String. If no content-encoding
        property had been set on the input Message, it will use the "UTF-8"
        charset by default. If you need to override that default setting, you
        can configure an instance of
        <classname>SimpleMessageConverter</classname>, set its
        "defaultCharset" property and then inject that into a
        <classname>RabbitTemplate</classname> instance.</para>

        <para>If the content-type property value of the input Message is set
        to "application/x-java-serialized-object", the
        <classname>SimpleMessageConverter</classname> will attempt to
        deserialize (rehydrate) the byte array into a Java object. While that
        might be useful for simple prototyping, it's generally not recommended
        to rely on Java serialization since it leads to tight coupling between
        the producer and consumer. Of course, it also rules out usage of
        non-Java systems on either side. With AMQP being a wire-level
        protocol, it would be unfortunate to lose much of that advantage with
        such restrictions. In the next two sections, we'll explore some
        alternatives for passing rich domain object content without relying on
        Java serialization.</para>

        <para>For all other content-types, the
        <classname>SimpleMessageConverter</classname> will return the Message
        body content directly as a byte array.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Converting To a Message</title>

        <para>When converting to a Message from an arbitrary Java Object, the
        <classname>SimpleMessageConverter</classname> likewise deals with byte
        arrays, Strings, and Serializable instances. It will convert each of
        these to bytes (in the case of byte arrays, there is nothing to
        convert), and it will set the content-type property accordingly. If
        the Object to be converted does not match one of those types, the
        Message body will be null.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>JsonMessageConverter</title>

      <para>As mentioned in the previous section, relying on Java
      serialization is generally not recommended. One rather common
      alternative that is more flexible and portable across different
      languages and platforms is JSON (JavaScript Object Notation). An
      implementation is available and can be configured on any
      <classname>RabbitTemplate</classname> instance to override its usage of
      the <classname>SimpleMessageConverter</classname> default.</para>

      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;bean class="org.springframework.amqp.rabbit.core.RabbitTemplate"&gt;
    &lt;property name="connectionFactory" ref="rabbitConnectionFactory"/&gt;
    &lt;property name="messageConverter"&gt;
        &lt;bean class="org.springframework.amqp.support.converter.JsonMessageConverter"&gt;
            &lt;!-- if necessary, override the DefaultClassMapper --&gt;
            &lt;property name="classMapper" ref="customClassMapper"/&gt;
        &lt;/bean&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>MarshallingMessageConverter</title>

      <para>Yet another option is the
      <classname>MarshallingMessageConverter</classname>. It delegates to the
      Spring OXM library's implementations of the
      <interfacename>Marshaller</interfacename> and
      <interfacename>Unmarshaller</interfacename> strategy interfaces. You can
      read more about that library <ulink
      url="http://static.springsource.org/spring/docs/3.0.x/spring-framework-reference/html/oxm.html">here</ulink>.
      In terms of configuration, it's most common to provide the constructor
      argument only since most implementations of
      <interfacename>Marshaller</interfacename> will also implement
      <interfacename>Unmarshaller</interfacename>.</para>

      <programlisting language="xml">&lt;bean class="org.springframework.amqp.rabbit.core.RabbitTemplate"&gt;
    &lt;property name="connectionFactory" ref="rabbitConnectionFactory"/&gt;
    &lt;property name="messageConverter"&gt;
        &lt;bean class="org.springframework.amqp.support.converter.MarshallingMessageConverter"&gt;
            &lt;constructor-arg ref="someImplemenationOfMarshallerAndUnmarshaller"/&gt;
        &lt;/bean&gt;
    &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="broker-configuration">
    <title>Configuring the broker</title>

    <para>The AMQP specification describes how the protocol can be used to
    configure Queues, Exchanges and Bindings on the broker. These operations
    which are portable from the 0.8 specification and higher are present in
    the AmqpAdmin interface in the org.springframework.amqp.core package. The
    RabbitMQ implementation of that class is RabbitAdmin located in the
    org.springframework.amqp.rabbit.core package. Any many configuration and
    management functions are broker specific and not included in the AMQP
    specification, the interface RabbitBrokerOperations and its implementation
    RabbitBrokerAdmin located in the org.springframework.amqp.rabbit.admin
    package is provided to fill that gap.</para>

    <para>The AmqpAdmin interface is based on using the Spring AMQP domain
    abstractions and is shown below:</para>

    <programlisting language="java">public interface AmqpAdmin {

    // Exchange Operations 

    void declareExchange(Exchange exchange);

    void deleteExchange(String exchangeName);

    // Queue Operations

    Queue declareQueue();

    void declareQueue(Queue queue);

    void deleteQueue(String queueName);

    void deleteQueue(String queueName, boolean unused, boolean empty);

    void purgeQueue(String queueName, boolean noWait);

    // Binding Operations

    void declareBinding(Binding binding);

}</programlisting>

    <para>The declareQueue() method defined a queue on the broker whose name
    is automatically created. The additional properties of this auto-generated
    queue are exclusive=true, autoDelete=true, and durable=false.<note>
        <para>Removing a binding was not introduced until the 0.9 version of
        the AMQP spec.</para>
      </note></para>

    <para>The RabbitMQ implementation of this interface is RabbitAdmin which
    when configured using Spring XML would look like this:<programlisting
    language="xml">&lt;bean id="cf" class="org.springframework.amqp.rabbit.connection.SingleConnectionFactory"&gt;
    &lt;constructor-arg value="localhost"/&gt;
    &lt;property name="username" value="guest"/&gt;
    &lt;property name="password" value="guest"/&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;

&lt;bean id="amqpAdmin" class="org.springframework.amqp.rabbit.core.RabbitAdmin"&gt;
    &lt;constructor-arg ref="cf"/&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting></para>

    <para>The class AbstractAmqpConfiguration can also be used to configure an
    instance of the AmqpAmin interface. The base class
    AbstractAmqpConfiguration is located in the package
    org.springframework.amqp.config and is shown in part below.</para>

    <programlisting language="java">@Configuration
public abstract class AbstractAmqpConfiguration implements ApplicationContextAware, SmartLifecycle {

  @Bean
  public abstract AmqpAdmin amqpAdmin();

  // the rest omitted for brevity.
}</programlisting>

    <para>The part that is omitted is related to the implementation of
    SmartLifecycle which is responsible for querying the container for all
    Queues, Exchanges, and Bindings that are defined in the DI container and
    declaring them to the broker. Thus if you are using the @Configuration
    style of configuration, you can simply create Queue, Exchange, and Binding
    bean definitions and they will be declared to the broker once the
    application has started.</para>

    <para>If you are using RabbitMQ as your broker, the additional abstract
    @Configuration class can be used to bootstrap an implementation of
    AmqpAdmin as shown below</para>

    <programlisting language="java">@Configuration
public abstract class AbstractRabbitConfiguration extends AbstractAmqpConfiguration {

  @Bean 
  public abstract RabbitTemplate rabbitTemplate();

  @Bean
  public AmqpAdmin amqpAdmin() {
    this.amqpAdmin = new RabbitAdmin(rabbitTemplate().getConnectionFactory());
    return this.amqpAdmin;
  }
}</programlisting>

    <para>This leaves it up to you to provide an implementation of the
    rabbitTemplate method in your application specific subclass. For example,
    using the Stock sample application, there is the @Configuration class
    AbstractStockRabbitConfiguration which in turn has
    RabbitClientConfiguration and RabbitServerConfiguration subclasses. The
    code for AbstractStockRabbitConfiguration is show below</para>

    <programlisting language="java">@Configuration
public abstract class AbstractStockAppRabbitConfiguration extends AbstractRabbitConfiguration {

    @Bean
    public ConnectionFactory connectionFactory() {
        SingleConnectionFactory connectionFactory = new SingleConnectionFactory("localhost");
        connectionFactory.setUsername("guest");
        connectionFactory.setPassword("guest");
        return connectionFactory;
    }

    @Bean 
    public RabbitTemplate rabbitTemplate() {
        RabbitTemplate template = new RabbitTemplate(connectionFactory());
        template.setMessageConverter(jsonMessageConverter());
        configureRabbitTemplate(template);
        return template;
    }

    @Bean
    public MessageConverter jsonMessageConverter() {
        return new JsonMessageConverter();
    }

    @Bean
    public TopicExchange marketDataExchange() {
        return new TopicExchange("app.stock.marketdata");
    }

    // additional code omitted for brevity

}</programlisting>

    <para>In the Stock application, the server is configured using the
    following @Configuration class</para>

    <programlisting language="java">@Configuration
public class RabbitServerConfiguration extends AbstractStockAppRabbitConfiguration  {

    @Bean
    public Queue stockRequestQueue() {		
        return new Queue("app.stock.request");	
    }
}</programlisting>

    <para>This is the end of the whole inheritance chain of @Configuration
    classes. The end result is the the TopicExchange and Queue will be
    declared to the broker upon application startup. There is no binding of
    the TopicExchange to a queue in the server configuration, as that is done
    in the client application. The stock request queue however is
    automatically bound to the AMQP default exchange - this behavior is
    defined by the specification.</para>

    <para>The client @Configuration class is a little more interesting and is
    show below.</para>

    <programlisting language="java">@Configuration
public class RabbitClientConfiguration extends AbstractStockAppRabbitConfiguration {

    @Value("${stocks.quote.pattern}")
    private String marketDataRoutingKey;

    @Bean
    public Queue marketDataQueue() {		
        return amqpAdmin().declareQueue();
    }
	
    /**
     * Binds to the market data exchange. Interested in any stock quotes.
     */	
    @Bean
    public Binding marketDataBinding() {		
        return BindingBuilder.from(
                marketDataQueue()).to(marketDataExchange()).with(marketDataRoutingKey);
    }

    // additional code omitted for brevity

}</programlisting>

    <para>The client is declaring another queue via the declareQueue() method
    on the AmqpAdmin, and it binds that queue to the market data exchange with
    a routing pattern that is externalized in a properties file.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Exception Handling</title>

    <para>TODO: Add documentation for the runtime exception hierarchy.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>JMX Monitoring</title>

    <para>All the methods in the RabbitBrokerAdmin class are exposed through
    JMX through the use of the @ManagedOperations annotation. Please refer to
    the sample application for how to configure spring to export the
    RabbitBro</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
