<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="spring-integration-amqp">
  <title>Spring Integration AMQP Support</title>

  <section id="spring-integration-amqp-introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The <ulink url="http://springsource.org/spring-integration">Spring Integration</ulink> project
      will include AMQP Channel Adapters and Gateways that build upon the Spring AMQP project as soon
      as the Spring AMQP project has a GA release. For now, those adapters are under development in the
      Spring Integration <ulink url="https://src.springsource.org/svn/spring-integration/sandbox/spring-integration-amqp/">sandbox</ulink>.
      In Spring Integration, "Channel Adapters" are unidirectional (one-way) whereas "Gateways" are
      bidirectional (request-reply). Ultimately, we will be providing an inbound-channel-adapter,
      outbound-channel-adapter, inbound-gateway, and outbound-gateway. As of the time of the Spring AMQP 1.0
      Milestone 1 release, the 2 Channel Adapters are available. As mentioned, they are still in the "sandbox"
      and as such are subject to change and should not be depended upon in a production environment. That said,
      if you check out the project, you should be able to build it with Maven and experiment for yourself.</para>

    <para>When the AMQP adapters are part of an official Spring Integration release, the documentation
      will be available as part of the Spring Integration distribution. In the meantime, we will just
      provide a quick overview of the current state of that development here.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Inbound Channel Adapter</title>

    <para>To receive AMQP Messages from a Queue, configure an &lt;inbound-channel-adapter&gt;</para>

    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<amqp:inbound-channel-adapter queue-name="some.queue" channel="fromAMQP" connection-factory="rabbitConnectionFactory"/>]]></programlisting>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Outbound Channel Adapter</title>

    <para>To send AMQP Messages to an Exchange, configure an &lt;outbound-channel-adapter&gt;.
      A 'routing-key' may optionally be provided in addition to the exchange name.</para>

    <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<amqp:outbound-channel-adapter channel="toAMQP" exchange-name="some.exchange" routing-key="foo" amqp-template="rabbitTemplate"/>]]></programlisting>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Inbound Gateway</title>

    <para>Coming Soon</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Outbound Gateway</title>

    <para>Coming Soon</para>
  </section>

</chapter>
